A Guide to the James Whitcomb Riley Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7133-f
James Whitcomb Riley Collection 1880-1915
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7133-f
ca. 65 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [1963 December 17] 1966 April 8
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Poem, "Them Flowers," inscribed, "To My Good Friend Eugene Debs", 1887 Sep 13; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Cyclone," inscribed, "For Joseph P. Smith, " pasted on a sheet with a 1 p., TLS, 1891 Feb 27, M. H. de Young to Smith and a 1 p., ALS, 1891 Feb 27, George [Rontrell] to Smith, 1891 Mar 4; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "We know, not every morrow can be sad...," on fly-leaf of Old-Fashioned Roses, with index, [1892]; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "America's Thanksgiving", inscribed to J. H. Tennant, 1900 Nov 17; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "When She Comes Home", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Two versions of poem, "Naughty Claude" on same sheet, n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Watches of the Night", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Moonshiner's Serenade", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "Sleep", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "One leads us through the watches of the night...", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
- Letters
  - [ James Whitcomb Riley] to "Dear Woman", 1880 Jun 30; ALS, 5 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to D. L. Milliken, 1884 Nov 24; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to [J. N.] Matthews, 1886 Sep 29; ALS, 2 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to John Boyle O'Reilly, 1886 Dec 3; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Charles Whiting, 1887 Nov 9; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Carey, 1888 Apr 27; ALS, 2 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Mrs. Boyesen, 1889 Dec 30; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Mr. Stoddart, with Indianapolis News clipping about Riley, 1890 Feb 15; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to [Venowine], 1890 Feb 19; ALS, 2 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to [Robert Underwood] Johnson, 1890 Jul 15; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Jahu DeWitt Miller, 1890 Dec 3; ALS, 2 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Eugene Field, 1891 Jan 16; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to H[jalmar] H[jorth] Boyesen, 1891 Jan 19; ALS, 2 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Mr. Smith, 1891 Mar 5; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Kate Douglas Wiggin, 1891 Mar 11; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Madison Cawein, 1891 Aug 11; ALS, 2 p. w/env
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Madison Cawein, 1891 Dec 2; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Horace P. Chandler, 1892 Feb 6; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to George, 1892 Nov 30; ALS, 3 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1892 Dec 26; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Joseph P. Smith, 1893 Jan 14; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Jeannette Leonard Gilder, 1893 Dec 19; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Mr. Ellwanger, 1894 Feb 11; ALS, 3 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Carey, 1894 Aug 27; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1895 May 25; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Henry E. Lower, 1895 Dec 19; ALS, 1 p. w/env
  - James Whitcomb Riley to [James] Bogle, 1897 Feb 11; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to William W. Ellsworth, 1897 Aug 9; ALS, 3 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Edmund Clarence Stedman, 1898 Feb 4; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Miss [McKinney], 1898 Jul 23; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Mr. Miller, 1898 Nov 6; ALS, 1 p.
  - Envelope, [ James Whitcomb Riley] to Wallace A. Cathcart, 1899 Jan 21; Envelope
  - James Whitcomb Riley to DeWitt Miller, 1899 Nov 25; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Emma Carleton, 1900 Feb 21; ALS, 1 p. w/env
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1900 Jul 23; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1900 Aug 25; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Mrs. H. F. Hovey, 1900 Sep 5; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to James C. Young, 1901 Nov 12; ALS, 1 p. w/env
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1902 Jun 4; ALS, 1 p. w/env
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1902 Jul 3; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1903 May 23; ALS, 2 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1904 Mar 7; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to F. C. Colver, 1907 May 10; TLS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1908 Sep 15; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to W. W. Ellsworth, 1910 Apr 1; ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to [Amelie Rives] Troubetzkoy, 1915 Oct 19; TLS, 1 p.
- Photographs
  - James Whitcomb Riley, inscribed, "With all best greetings and esteem", 1897 Dec 2; Photo, signed
  - Picturing James Whitcomb Riley, n.d.; 5 commemorative stamps
  - James Whitcomb Riley, standing, inscribed, "To Charles Warren Stoddard", Photo signed
  - James Whitcomb Riley, head and shoulders, inscribed, "With best greetings and esteem", Photo signed
  - James Whitcomb Riley, inscribed, "To Joaquin Miller-'King and Comrade' ", Photo signed
- Miscellaneous
  - "Brave love," James Whitcomb Riley's favorite poem, with a letter from Riley printed on the same sheet, n.d.; Clipping